Hello, today's דף Daf is י"ב. Yud Bais. We pick up on
the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה Mishna on י"א עמוד ב'.
Yud Aleph Amud Bais. The משנה Mishna has moved to the issue
about the death of the... well we were just discussing the previous
משנה Mishna before that, the death of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
and this משנה Mishna speaks about
let's say there's a change in the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so
it's whoever is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or let's say the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies right after גמר דין Gmar Din but
before the guy went to the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. So the
basic rule is, whoever is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol at the
moment of גמר דין Gmar Din when the judgment is passed,
and when that כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, even if the guy
before he went to the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, if that כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol dies, he then no longer has to be in
exile. If there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol at the moment of
גמר דין, Gmar Din, then this guy never gets free.
Any one of those three, right?
Any one of the כהן גדולs, Kohen Gadol yes. But anyway I'm
just going to call it כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Anyway, so that's
the key is גמר דין, Gmar Din, that's the moment. Whoever the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is then, if there's no כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol he never goes free, and then if the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol dies immediately after, even if he hasn't yet gone into exile,
he does go free. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama?
What's the reason that he goes free after גמר דין Gmar Din
before he's gone into exile? אמר אביי קל וחומר, Amar Abaye Kal
Vachomer, a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. ומה מי שגלה כבר יצא, Umah
Mi Shegalah Kvar Yatza, somebody who's already been in exile goes free,
יצא עכשיו מי שלא גלה אינו דין שלא יגלה? Yatza Achshav Mi
Shelo Galah Eino Din Shelo Yigaleh? So somebody therefore who's never been
in exile, who's already halfway out, he isn't even in yet, how
much more so should he not go... how much more so should
he go free? Of course
it's a little bizarre קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, which the גמרא Gemara
responds back. ודילמה, V'dilma, says the גמרא, Gemara, האי דגלה איכפר ליה,
Hai Degalah Ikpfer Lei,
what do you mean? The guy who went into exile at least
he got some degree of atonement for being in exile. You could
say he got his punishment to some degree. האי דלא גלה לא,
Hai Delo Galah Lo, the guy who never went into exile, no,
so you know, he didn't get any atonement. So on the one
hand you could argue since he isn't in yet, we shouldn't put
him in, but it's harder to take somebody out, you know, it's
easier if somebody's already not in to keep him out than to
take somebody out. So that's the קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. On the
other hand, the guy who went into exile got some degree of
his punishment. So the גמרא Gemara says, מידי, Midi, so now a
very important line in the גמרא, Gemara, just like a throwaway line.
מידי גלות קמכפרה, Midi Galus Kamchapra,
what, you think it's the exile that atones? No. מיתת כהן היא
דמכפרה, Misas Kohen Hi De'mechaphra, it's the death of the כהן Kohen
that atones. So Michael says wait, I do think it's the exile
that atones. So תוספות Tosafot also thinks that. So if you look
at תוספות, Tosafot, מידי גלות קמכפרה, Midi Galus Kamchapra, תוספות Tosafot says,
תימא אין הכי נמי, Teima Ein Hachi Nami, yeah, it is the
exile. מיד אמר בריש מכילתין, Mi De'amar B'reish Mechiltin, we say at
the beginning of the מסכת, Masechet, הם שלא עשו מעלה יגלו כדי
שתהא להם כפרה, Hem Shelo Assu Ma'alah Yiglu Kdei Shetehei Lahem Kapara,
you know, אלמא גלות מכפר, Alma Galus Mechaper, the גמרא Gemara explicitly
speaks about let them go into exile, the exile is a כפרה,
Kapara, that's normally how we think about it. So תוספות Tosafot says,
ויש לומר דהכא כפרה לפטור מגלות קאמר. V'yesh Lomar Dehacha Kapara Liftur
Migalus Ka'amar. No,
there's two כפרות Kaparas we're talking about here. There's what is the
atonement for your sin, I mean you know, for the sin of
the negligence, okay, that is the exile. Then there's what serves as
the atonement... a funny word of atonement because you're not suffering, but
what serves... but you know, a קרבן Korban is also an atonement.
When you bring a קרבן, Korban, I mean you know, that gets
into all sorts of challenging theology about you know, the death of
the righteous atones. But right, you know, death of a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol lets you go free. But you bring, you know, on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur a קרבן Korban is brought and that atones,
you didn't do anything for it. So atonement here doesn't necessarily mean
somehow you suffer, you know, it means that some type of a
ritual act was done that sets the slate clean. So תוספות Tosafot
says when it comes to freeing you from exile, it is the
death of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that is the act of
freeing you from exile. Yeah, where... but in terms of atonement for
the negligence of the death that you caused, that is the exile.
Okay, so it's an ironic situation that the person now doesn't have
to go into exile, but never gets the experience of גלות Galus
to effect atonement for the original sin, right? So that's an interesting
thing. So let's just read תוספות, Tosafot, ויש לומר דהכא כפרה לפטור
מגלות קאמר דהבא למיפטר מי שלא גלה דמיתת כהן גדול תועיל לפטרו
מגלות מקל וחומר. V'yesh Lomar Dehacha Kapara Liftur Migalus Ka'amar Dehava Lameipatar
Mi Shelo Galah De'misas Kohen Gadol Toil Liptoro Migalus M'kal Vachomer. Okay,
so
anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says that. So the death of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is the מכפר, Mechaper, as it were, the act
that frees you from גלות. Galus. But the גלות Galus is the
experience that atones for the sin. So it's an interesting balance. Okay
let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. אם עד שלא נגמר
דינו. Im Ad Shelo Nigmar Dino. Now this is if... a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol was appointed during the trial proceedings, it goes by
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who is in office at the time
of the גמר דין. Gmar Din. מנא הני מילי? Mena Hanei Milei?
Where's this from? אמר רב כהנא דאמר קרא, Amar Rav Kahana De'amar
Kra, the verse says, וישב בה עד מות הכהן הגדול, V'yashav Bah
Ad Mos HaKohen HaGadol, he will dwell in the עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat until the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, אשר משח אותו בשמן
הקודש, Asher Mashach Oso B'shemen HaKodesh, that he anointed him with the
holy oil. So the simple reading of the verse is, he, the
person who is being exiled for having killed this person, anointed the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, right? He shall dwell in the עיר מקלט
Ir Miklat until the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who he anointed. he
anointed with the holy oil dies. What do you mean he anointed
with the holy oil?
So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי הוא משחו? V'chi hu meshacho? Was
he the one who anointed the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? אלא שנמשח
בימיו. Ela shenimshach b'yamav.
He anointed means the anointing happened in his day. Okay, so it
says until the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol who was anointed in his time. So that means even the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who was anointed during the trial proceedings, and
whoever was the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol at the time of the
גמר דין, Gmar Din, even if it was a new כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, or a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who was anointed during
his time, that is the- it's that כהן גדול Kohen Gadol whose
death frees him. Okay. If there is no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
at the time of the גמר דין, Gmar Din, he never goes
free. And interestingly, the גמרא- Gemara Yeah, the גמרא's Gemara going
to do it for קל וחומר. Kal V'chomer. Right, even if the
כהן גדול- Kohen Gadol
Right, but it's the act of death, it's not the absence of
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. But what's interesting is the גמרא, Gemara,
I'm just going to warn you, completely skips over the three cases
in the משנה Mishnah that the person never goes free. There's no
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol around at the time of the גמר דין.
Gmar Din. That is sort of a logical derivation from the way
we've been framing it until now. Somebody killed a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Okay, because there could be a new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
at the time of גמר דין Gmar Din just because you killed
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, right, doesn't mean that there isn't a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol at the time of גמר דין. Gmar Din.
Right, whatever, right. And a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who actually committed
murder. Okay, now that you understand because he- if he's the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, right, then his death would free him. But as
Michael says, but maybe there's another- but maybe, you know, presumably if
he did it and he's in exile, they appoint a new כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. So why could that new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
not- So those things, you know, you certainly have- like you understand
a little bit the intuitive logic of that, but the גמרא Gemara
never explains how we know that that's factual הלכה. Halacha. Okay, and
now we move on to other- other points. So אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, נקטינן, Naktinan, we take as a הלכה-
Halacha
מאי הוה ליה
למיעבד?
Mai hava
leh l'meivad?
Oh, did I skip a line? מאי הוה ליה למיעבד? Mai hava
leh l'meivad? אלא שנמשח בימיו. Ela shenimshach b'yamav. מאי הוה ליה למיעבד?
Mai hava leh l'meivad? Oh, thank you. מאי הוה ליה למיעבד? Mai
hava leh l'meivad? So now, thank you. So the גמרא Gemara asks,
you know, because we had this before when it was about praying
that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol shouldn't die and so on, it
assumes that if the death of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is
an atonement, right, the גמרא Gemara never really fully unpacked that, but
part of that has to do with the fact that the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol bears some responsibility for what happened, right? And the
גמרא Gemara mentioned that before, like you should have created a society
in which these types of things don't happen, you know, leaders have
responsibility when deaths occur in the society, preventable deaths. So therefore the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, that's if this guy was a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol when the actual death occurred. Okay, but this case the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was- was appointed during the trial proceedings, where
is his- like- responsibility for anything that happened? So if his death
is going to free the guy, the גמרא Gemara understands the implicit
logic in that is that he bears some of the responsibility, he,
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, for what has happened. But why- why
is that true when he was appointed during the trial proceedings, where's
his responsibility? So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי הוה ליה למיעבד? Mai
hava leh l'meivad? היה לו לבקש רחמים שיגמור דינו לזכות ולא ביקש.
Haya lo l'vakesh rachamim sheyigmor dino l'zechut v'lo vikesh.
No, he didn't have responsibility for the death, but he had responsibility
for the guy's- you know, for the guy being sentenced to exile,
because- you know, maybe he could have prayed- now what's his responsibility?
Maybe the guy deserved it. He could have prayed that the guy
would have gotten off free. But maybe justice was being served. I
mean, it's a little bizarre, pray that the guy shouldn't be found
guilty for something he really is guilty of? You know, so it's
very hard to understand at this stage. His- like- his responsibility is
the fact that the guy is in exile, and therefore his death
frees the guy, although it might be the right thing that the
guy's in exile. So I don't really know what to fully do
with this. Charlie, your hand's up?
Yeah. We also have a concept of just in general, מיתת צדיקים
מכפרת. mitat tzadikim mechaperet. And like you have these other אלו ואלו
ואלו. elu v'elu v'elu. You know, it could have just been any
צדיק, tzadik, but then, you know, how do you find-?
Right. Well, he represents the head of the religious establishment, right? You
have to understand, right, that before the whole rabbinic period, right, the-
the rabbinic leaders were the כהנים, Kohanim, so he is- he represents
the head of the rabbinic establishment- of the whatever, religious establishment.
Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, נקטינן, Naktinan, we have-
take as a principle, נגמר דינו ומת, Nigmar dino v'met, after somebody
had the גמר דין Gmar Din and then he died, okay, this
person who was supposed- not the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died, this
guy died. So he never went into exile. What are you supposed
to do with his dead body? מוליכין את עצמותיו לשם. Molichin et
atzmotav l'sham. You bury him- you bring him to an עיר מקלט
Ir Miklat and you bury him in an עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat.
Why? So he says, דכתיב, Dechtiv, לשוב לשבת בארץ עד מות הכהן,
lashuv lashevet ba'aretz ad mot hakohen, that he has to go back
to dwell in the land in the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat until
the הכהן hakohen dies. ואיזו היא ישיבה ש"בארץ", V'eizo hi yeshiva she-ba'aretz,
what is a dwelling that's "in the land", not "on the land",
"in the land", you know, underneath the land? So in the dirt.
So "in the land", הוי אומר זו קבורה. hevei omer zo kevurah.
So part of the הלכה Halacha of exile is that you're buried
in the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. So then it's not just the
guy who died now, a guy who's in exile who dies remains
buried in the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat.
And don't you put the bones with the father every year?
Nope, and we're about to say that. Okay, so once that's true,
then it's even true about the guy that had a גמר דין
Gmar Din and never went to exile, part of the דין Din
of exile is... which was passed on this person is that he's
buried in the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. Okay. תנא: Tana: מת קודם
שמת כהן. Meit kodem she'meit Kohen. I mean, the what he... it's
in the משנה Mishnah by the way. Look at the last narrow
line, you know, in the גמרא Gemara in the middle of the
משנה. Mishnah. It says: שם תהא דירתו שם תהא מיתתו שם תהא
קבורתו.
Sham tei dirato, sham tei misato, sham
tei kevurato. You see that line in the משנה? Mishnah? So he's
buried there. That's part of the דין Din of עיר מקלט. Ir
Miklat. So here this guy's buried even though he never lived there.
Wouldn't it be like a year later then they'd take him out?
No, but we didn't... no, we don't say that. Although we'll read
a line in a minute. Okay.
Okay, תנא: Tana: Let's finish the... they won't finish it? Let's say
he dies in the middle. Will they finish it in the middle?
No, if he dies then there's no גמר דין Gmar Din in
the middle of the proceeding.
תנא: Tana: מת קודם שמת כהן גדול, Meit kodem she'meit Kohen Gadol,
if he dies before the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, so he's
in the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat,
מוליכין עצמותיו על קברי אבותיו, molichin atzmoto al kivrei avotav, דכתיב: d'chtiv:
ישוב הרוצח אל ארץ אחוזתו. yashuv harotzeach el eretz achuzato. You bring
his bones, you carry them
on top of—that's a little translation—of his forefathers' grave, because it says
he shall return to the land of his inheritance.
איזהו ישוב שהיא ארץ אחוזתו? Eizehu yeshuv she'hi eretz achuzato? הוי אומר
זו קבורה. Hevei omer zu kevurah. It's burial. Now what the heck
is that saying? You said he's supposed to be buried there. So
it sounds a little bit, if you read it, that you take
his body and sort of dealing with Michael's problem about whatever happened
about being buried with one's fathers, and you could say well that's
the punishment, you don't get that, but you take the body,
you do a little visit
to the ancestral grave, and then you bring it back and you
bury it in the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. A little bit it
sounds that way. But רמבם Rambam reads this very different because the
word לשוב לשבת בארץ, lashuv lashevet ba'aretz, right, עד מות הכהן... ad
mot hakohen... well, actually no, לשוב לשבת lashuv lashevet is... I'm sorry,
ישוב הרוצח אל ארץ אחוזתו, yashuv harotzeach el eretz achuzato, that's once
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies. So the way the רמבם Rambam
reads this is, it's a little confusing because when he says מת
קודם שמת כהן גדול, meit kodem she'meit Kohen Gadol, the רמבם Rambam
inserts in that: and then the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died. So
what happens after the guy was buried in the עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat and then the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died? So the רמבם
Rambam says then you disinter his bones and bury him with his
father. Not after a year, after the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died.
And that's ישוב הרוצח—when yashuv harotzeach is ישוב הרוצח אל ארץ אחוזתו?
yashuv harotzeach el eretz achuzato? When the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies.
So the same way if he was alive he would get to
return, now even though he's dead his bones get to return to
his ancestral land, to his father's plot.
Okay. הוי אומר—okay, Hevei omer fine. זו קבורה. Zu kevurah. So that's
nice. That sort of allows at least eventually his bones to be
laid to rest.
Okay. נגמר דינו ונעשה כהן בן גרושה ובין חלוצה. Nigmar dino ve'na'aseh
Kohen ben Grusha ve'hein Chalutzah. Now let's say the guy had a
גמר דין Gmar Din and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was a
certain person, ראובן. Reuven. So now it's going to be ראובן כהן
גדול's Reuven Kohen Gadol death that's going to free him. And now
it is discovered that ראובן Reuven actually is
a פסול כהן. Pasul Kohen ראובן's Reuven mother was actually a גרושה,
Grusha, so he's a חלל. challal. Okay, so he never was a
כשר kosher כהן. Kohen. Alright, so what does that going to mean?
So is this guy now there was—turns out there was no official
real כהן גדול Kohen Gadol when the guy had a גמר דין.
Gmar Din. Is he trapped in the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat for
forever? So פליגי רבי אמי ורבי יצחק נפחא. peligi Rabbi Ammi ve'Rabbi
Yitzchak Nafcha. There's a debate. חד אמר מיתה כהונה וחד אמר בטלה
כהונה. Chad amar meita kehunah ve'chad amar batla kehunah. One says the
כהונה kehunah died, meaning it's like a death of the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. The death of his כהונה kehunah is the death of
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay? So the discovery that he is
a בן גרושה ben Grusha is like the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
was negated and therefore he goes free through that discovery. And the
other says no, retroactively there was no כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so
the guy is stuck. Okay. לימא בפלוגתא דרבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע קמיפלגי?
Leima biflugta de'Rabbi Eliezer ve'Rabbi Yehoshua kamifligi? Maybe this ties into another
debate? דתנן: Detnan: היה עומד ומקריב על גבי המזבח. hayah omeid umakriv
agabei mizbei'ach. A כהן Kohen. was there standing and bringing sacrifices on
the altar, ונודע שהוא בן גרושה ובין חלוצה. venoda shehu ben Grusha
ve'hein Chalutzah. And then it gets discovered in the middle of his
bringing sacrifices that he is the son of a גרושה Grusha or
a חלוצה Chalutzah and he's a פסול pasul כהן. Kohen רבי אליעזר
אומר כל קרבנות שהקריב פסולין. Rabbi Eliezer omer kol korbanot she'hikriv pesulin.
So that means he was never a כהן. Kohen. We'll just take
that to its logical conclusion. Retroactively any קרבן korban this person has
ever brought in his life is פסול. pasul You gotta go ahead
and inform all of the people and have them bring another קרבן.
korban. רבי
יהושע מכשיר. Rabbi Yehoshua machshir. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no,
his invalidity only starts now. Okay? So, so מאן דאמר מיתה—so man
d'amar meita if you say it's like the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
died, to רבי יהושע—that's Rabbi Yehoshua like רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. You
say he was a good כהן גדול Kohen Gadol until this minute,
and at this minute he stops being a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Okay? And therefore that's like the death of the כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Alright? So that would work because the new status, the פסול
pasul. status only begins now. Even that's a חידוש chiddush because you
could say he became פסול, pasul he didn't die. But at least
it works structurally that he was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol until
now, and that status until now, and only now the status changed.
So that's like מיתה. meita. And that would free the guy.
מאן דאמר בטלה, Man d'amar batla, that it was retroactively annulled and
he was never כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the guy is stuck,
כרבי אליעזר. ke'Rabbi Eliezer. That's like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That seems
like a ראיה. ra'ayah. is moving away from the debate. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, top of יב עמוד א: Yud Bais
Amud Aleph: אליבא דרבי אליעזר כולי עלמא לא פליגי. Aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer
kulei alma lo pligi. You're right. According to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
there's no question about it, right? If retroactively, if he says retroactively
he was a פסול pasul, כהן Kohen. and therefore the same is
true that all of his קרבנות Korbanot are no good, it means
there was no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol at the time of this
guy's גמר דין. Gmar Din. כי פליגי אליבא דרבי יהושע. Ki pligi
aliba de'Rabbi Yehoshua. The debate is according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua.
מאן דאמר מיתה Man de'amar mesa כרבי יהושע. ke'Rabbi Yehoshua. If you
say
it's like the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died, that's the simple application
of רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. He was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
until this moment, and this moment it ceased. ומן
דאמר בטלה, u'man de'amar batla, and the one that says
no, he was never כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, עד כאן, ad kan,
he would say the following. In general I would agree with רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that the קרבנות Korbanot that he would have brought
until now would be kosher. But עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהושע
התם, ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua hasam, but that's a special
הלכה halacha of קרבנות. Korbanos. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua only said his
ruling אלא elah only in that case, דכתיב ברך ה' חילו ופועל
ידיו תרצה. d'chsiv bareich Hashem cheilo ufo'al yadav tirtzeh. This is the
ברכה bracha to the כהנים. Kohanim. God should bless his, like, strength,
and he should and he should desire the act of his hands.
And the word תרצה tirtzeh is a classic קרבן korban word. So
the דרשה drasha is, so the acts of his hands is the
bringing of the קרבנות. Korbanot. And the word חילו cheilo is the
word of חולין. chullin. אפילו חולין שבו afilu cholin she'bo or חלל,
chalal, which is a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that is shown to
be a
בן גרושה. ben grusha. So even if it turns out that he
was a חלל, chalal, ברך ה' חילו ופועל ידיו תרצה. bareich Hashem
cheilo ufo'al yadav tirtzeh. The קרבנות Korbanot are still accepted. As long
as we were ignorant of it at the time, God will still
accept the קרבנות. Korbanot. So that's a special הלכה. halacha. It's a
good הלכה halacha to have in place so you don't have to
now have a thousand people have to rebring their קרבנות Korbanot and
nobody's keeping track anyway, okay? So that's the הלכה halacha that if
it turns out he wasn't known to be a חלל chalal and
it turns out he was a חלל, chalal, the קרבנות Korbanot are
good. But that's a special הלכה halacha by קרבנות. Korbanot. אבל הכא,
aval hacha, but here, אפילו רבי יהושע מודה, afilu Rabbi Yehoshua modeh,
even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would agree, say, this isn't about קרבנות,
Korbanot, and if somebody was a חלל, chalal, then he was never
really a real כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so this guy had a
גמר דין Gmar Din without a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and therefore
he's stuck for life. You had a question Charlie, yes.
Yeah, that פסוק pasuk is the ברכה bracha of משה רבינו Moshe
Rabbeinu to all of שבט לוי, shevet Levi, right?
Right, I understand, but that's how it's read. Okay, what can I
tell you? Especially the תרצה tirtzeh is a keyword that refers to
כהנים. kohanim.
I mean or refers to קרבנות.
korbanot. Okay. נגמר דינו. Nigmar dino. Now,
now it's said that once he has a גמר דין Gmar Din
he's there even if he is needed to like be a for
כלל ישראל klal Yisrael like יואב בן צרויה. Yoav ben Tzeruiah. All
right, now first of all, that's a bizarre הלכה halacha and I'm
sure I haven't done a can-can research yet, but like whatever happens
to פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? Right? If this is the guy that
we need to lead us into army, you know, it really matters
who your generals are, right? So like you know what? Be cause...
Okay, so there's a lo tas... there's you know what... there's an
עשה aseh whatever, you know, what's the פסוק? pasuk? וישב בה, v'yashav
bah, right? אשר נס שמה asher nas shamah
whatever,
fine, but you can't be מבטל mivatel the עשה aseh for the
sake of הצלת כלל ישראל? hatzalas klal Yisrael? So I don't really
understand that, but anyway the גמרא Gemara doesn't explore that. But because
it mentioned יואב בן צרויה, Yoav ben Tzeruiah, there, why of all
people to mention יואב בן צרויה? Yoav ben Tzeruiah? Because there's a
great story about יואב בן צרויה. Yoav ben Tzeruiah. I don't know
if you remember this, but on David on his deathbed he says
to שלמה, Shlomo, he says, yeah, go take care of that יואב
בן צרויה Yoav ben Tzeruiah guy because he killed those two major
generals of Israel and don't let him go down to his grave
you know in peace or whatever. So you know, he he was
he made blood at the time of at the time of peace
and make sure that he gets his
comeuppance. So then basically יואב בן צרויה Yoav ben Tzeruiah runs to
the בסי... מזבח mizbe'ach and he holds on to
the—We had this story already, we even did it like in one
of the גמרות. Gemaras.
Oh, did we? I don't even remember. In ברכות? Brochos? In חלק?
Cheilek? Okay. So he holds on to the מזבח mizbe'ach because you
know and then basically Dovid goes... שלמה Shlomo goes ahead and sends
what's his name, בניהו בן יהוידע Benaiahu ben Yehoyada and he sort
of kills him there in front of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So, okay,
so now why did he think to—first of all, that's so that's
a good story in the context of עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, because
he understood the idea of sanctuary, that the altar was a sanctuary
and you can't kill somebody holding on to the altar. Okay, but
what does the פסוק pasuk say actually by the מזבח? mizbe'ach? The
פסוק pasuk says by the מזבח mizbe'ach it says, וכי יזיד איש
על רעהו להרגו בערמה, v'chi yazid ish al re'ehu l'horgo b'ormah,
if somebody kills somebody intentionally, מעם מזבחי תקחנו למות. me'im mizbechi tikachenu
lamus.
You even have to rip him off of the altar to be
put to death. So the implicit point is—That if
you're holding on to the altar—No, no, one minute.
The implicit point is that that's if he killed him intentionally, the
altar does not serve as sanctuary. וכי יזיד איש על רעהו להרגו
בערמה. v'chi yazid ish al re'ehu l'horgo b'ormah.
But it sounds like if he killed unintentionally, בשוגג, b'shogeg, the מזבח
mizbe'ach would serve as a type of an עיר מקלט Ir Miklat
and that actually is the הלכה, halacha, that the מזבח mizbe'ach serves
as a type of an עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, we'll see in
the גמרא Gemara exactly what the parameters are for somebody who killed
בשוגג. b'shogeg. It didn't work for יואב Yoav cause יואב Yoav killed
במזיד. b'meizid. Okay, but let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
And the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה אמר רב:
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: שתי טעויות טעה יואב. shtei ta'uyot ta'ah
Yoav.
יואב Yoav made two mistakes באותה שעה. be-otah sha'ah. דכתיב וינס יואב
אל אהל ה' ויחזק בקרנות המזבח. de-chtiv va-yanos Yoav el ohel Hashem
va-yachazek be-karnot ha-mizbe'ach. טעה, ta'ah,
so he held onto the horns of the altar. טעה, ta'ah, he
erred, שאינו קולט אלא גגו. she-eino kolet ela gago. It says מעם
מזבחי, me-im mizbechi, so it's only the top of the altar, not,
you can't be standing and holding onto the horns. I guess you
have to throw yourself on top of the altar.
In such a...
I don't know, maybe touch it, maybe. והוא תפס בקרנותיו. ve-hu tafas
be-karnotav.
He held on to the horns there. He's on top.
Apparently it means the actual roof. והוא תפס בקרנותיו. ve-hu tafas be-karnotav.
He only held on to the horns. טעה שאינו קולט אלא מזבח
בית עולמים. ta'ah she-eino kolet ela mizbe'ach beit olamim. And also it's
מעם מזבחי, me-im mizbechi, מזבחי המיוחד לי. mizbechi ha-meyuchad li. It's only
the one single altar, the one in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
והוא תפס מזבח של שילה. ve-hu tafas mizbe'ach shel Shilo. Now רש"י
Rashi says actually it's not שילה. Shilo. The dating is wrong, but
it means the מזבח mizbe'ach that דוד David made temporarily in the
place where the ארון aron was being kept, but they didn't have
a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash yet. Okay, now of course what's fascinating
about this גמרא Gemara is it didn't also say and he erred
that he was a מזיד meizid and not a שוגג, shogeg, right?
So that I really don't understand at all why the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. אביי אמר בהא נמי מיטע טעה. Abaye amar be-ha
nami mi-tata ta'ah. He also made the third mistake. טעה שאינו קולט
אלא כהן ועבודה בידו. ta'ah she-eino kolet ela kohen va-avodah be-yado. And
I don't know how we know that, but it's only somebody who
belongs with the altar, somebody who basically is doing the עבודה avodah
and is a כהן, kohen,
and while he's doing the עבודה, avodah, you can't take him away
from it. Okay. והוא זר. ve-hu zar. And he was obviously a
non-כהן. kohen. So again, I have no idea how we know that
point. Now, I should say and again what's also fascinatingly that's absent
is the fact that he was a מזיד. meizid. But רמב"ם Rambam
has a fascinating הלכה halacha here, and I didn't get a chance
to look at where רמב"ם Rambam gets this from, but I want
to read you what רמב"ם Rambam says, because רמב"ם Rambam a little
bit deals with the problem that I just said which is
that he was a מזיד. meizid. And so listen to the רמב"ם,
Rambam, hold on, let me just get
it.
Yes,
so first רמב"ם Rambam says even if somebody who is a שוגג
shogeg and who has taken refuge to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you don't
let him stay there. You sort of appoint him some שומרים shomrim
and you basically accompany him to an עיר מקלט, ir miklat, but
at least it protects him while he's there. But then the רמב"ם
Rambam says the following: במה דברים אמורים במחויב גלות. be-meh devarim amurim
be-mechuyav galut.
When is this true that the מזבח mizbe'ach serves as an עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, you know, with all these conditions in the גמרא,
Gemara, you're a כהן, kohen, you're holding on to the right place,
or what's the other one? Oh, מזבח בית
עולמים. mizbe'ach beit olamim. When does that serve as a type of
an עיר מקלט ir miklat if somebody killed בשוגג. be-shogeg.
במה דברים אמורים במחויב גלות, be-meh devarim amurim be-mechuyav galut, אבל מי
שפחד מן המלך, aval mi she-pachad min ha-melech, I wonder where he's
getting this, שלא יהרגנו בדין המלכות. she-lo ye-hargenu be-din ha-malchut. Somebody who
in this case, somebody who is afraid that the king shouldn't execute
him because of the powers that the king has to do as
he wishes. או מבית דין שלא יהרגנו בהוראת שעה. o mi-beit din
she-lo ye-hargenu be-hora'at sha'ah. Or he wants to escape a בית דין
beit din killing him not because it's his legal judgment
but because the בית דין beit din serves as some emergency measures
they felt it was important to execute him. וברח למזבח ונסמך לו.
ve-barach la-mizbe'ach ve-nismach lo. ואפילו היה זר. va-afillu hayah zar.
And he went and
leaned on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, even a non-כהן. kohen. הרי זה ניצל.
harei zeh nitzal. He is protected. ואין לוקחים אותו מעם המזבח למות
לעולם. ve-ein lokchim oto me-im ha-mizbe'ach lamut le-olam. And you would never
take him, you'd let him stay there and remain protected. So that's
יואב's Yoav's case. So it's quite bizarre. The גמרא Gemara treats it
like
יואב Yoav was failed because of these technicalities. They ignored the fact
that he was מזיד meizid anyway. And the רמב"ם Rambam actually says
actually the יואב Yoav case should work because it was not, he
didn't have a דין בית דין din beit din to kill him.
Yeah, he didn't have a דין בית דין. din beit din. So
I don't know where the רמב"ם Rambam is getting it from. I'll
just say he got it from the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. I don't know.
Maybe I haven't seen the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, I'm behind in the ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. But it's quite a different idea than you get from our
גמרא. Gemara. Now let's just continue, Michael, okay, because we've got to
move on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ריש
לקיש: amar Reish Lakish: since we talked about these three errors about
גלות galut and יואב, Yoav, שלוש טעויות עתיד שרו של רומי לטעות.
shalosh ta'uyot atid saro shel Romi lit'ot. Three errors will the officer,
meaning the angel of Rome, who is like the divine power over
in Rome,
whatever the heavenly power. Okay, so God is eventually going to kill
that angel for all of the evil that Rome did against the
Jews and so on. And that angel is going to want to
run to an עיר מקלט ir miklat to protect himself. Sort of
similar to the יואב, Yoav, like it wasn't a killing בשוגג, be-shogeg,
it was killing people you shouldn't kill and now you're trying to
go to a מקלט miklat and protect yourself. One minute, Charlie. דכתיב
מי זה בא מאדום, de-chtiv mi zeh ba me-Edom, who is the
one coming from אדום? Edom? חמוץ בגדים מבצרה, chamutz begadim mi-Botzrah, who
has like ruddy garments from בצרה, Botzrah, which is a... So imagine
God. God just came from אדום Edom to slaughter the angel of
אדום, Edom, you know, in the, in the eschatological period, and his
blood and his garments are red, because the angel has been, because
he killed the angel. So, טעה, To'eh, so here was the mistake
that this angel meant, because he went to בצרה Botzrah to protect
himself. טעה שאינה קולטת אלא בצר, To'eh she-eina koletet ela Betzer, והוא
גלה לבצרה. v'hu gala le-Botzrah. Right, בצר Betzer was one of the
ערי מקלט. arei miklat. He got confused, בצר, Betzer, בצרה. Botzrah. Alright,
you should have spent more time learning תורה Torah than giving, than,
than afflicting בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. טעה שאינה קולטת אלא שוגג, To'eh
she-eina koletet ela shogeg, והוא מזיד, v'hu meizid, whoops, accidental, which is
fascinating that that was missing from the יואב Yoav discussion. והוא מזיד
היה. V'hu meizid haya. טעה שאינה קולטת אלא אדם, To'eh she-eina koletet
ela adam, it only works for people, והוא מלאך, v'hu malach, he's
an
angel. Okay. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, the altar שילה Shilo had been destroyed
by—I said that, I said רש״י Rashi said שילה Shilo was incorrect
in terms of the chronology. רש״י Rashi re-reads the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, עיר מקלט לא
ניתנו לקבורה, Ir miklat lo nitnu l'kevura, דכתיב de-chsiv ומגרשיהם יהיו להם
לבהמתם ולרכושם ושם לכל חייתם. u-migrasheihem yiheyu lahem livhemtam u-l'rekhusham v'sham l'khol
chaitam. לחיים ניתנו ולא לקבורה. L'chayim nitnu v'lo l'kevura. Okay, so you're
not supposed to get buried in the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, it's
supposed to be for living, not for burial. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, we just said that part of the הלכה halakha
was that he gets buried there. מיתיבי, Meitivei, שמה, shama, שמה תהא
דירתו שמה תהא מיתתו שמה תהא קבורתו. shama tehei dirato shama tehei
mitato shama tehei kevurato. That's where he's buried. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, רוצח שאני rotzeach shani דגלי ביה רחמנא. degali beih Rachmana.
No, no, no, the murderer, the people that are sent there in
exile, they get buried there. But the inhabitants, remember, these were the
cities of the לויים. Leviyim. So the לויים, Leviyim, they don't get
buried there. The לויים, Leviyim, you know, their cemetery is out of
the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. It's only for the, for the murderers
that were sent there, they have to remain buried there. Okay, and
there the תורה Torah is explicit. כשם שעיר קולטת, Keshem she-ir koletet,
the same way the city is a refuge, is a sanctuary, so
is the תחום, tchum, the area immediately outside, presumably the two thousand
אמה. amah. And in the תורה, Torah, by the way, when it
speaks about the ערי הלויים, arei ha-Leviyim, it speaks about giving them
a מגרש migrash and שדה, sadeh, giving them like, you know, fields
and giving them, yards or whatever, on the outskirts of the city.
One פסוק pasuk says a thousand אמה, amah, one says two thousand
אמה. amah. So the general way the רבנים rabbanim resolve it is
that they say the first thousand אמה amah is like greenery and
yards, like suburban type of whatever, and then two thousand, from one
thousand to two thousand, that's the fields for growing stuff. So two
thousand אמה amah around the city is the תחום, tchum, and the
two thousand אמה amah also serves as part as refuge if you
make it into that zone.
רמינהו, Reminehu, says let me ask you on this,
וישב בה, v'yashav bah, בה ולא בתחומה, bah v'lo bi-tchumah, only in
the city is it refuge, not in, or that seems to be
what it's saying, not in its environs. אמר אביי לא קשיא, Amar
Abaye lo kashya, כאן לקלוט כאן לדור. kan liklot kan ladur. No,
no, no, that's saying that you're not allowed to live, right, you
have to live, you make your house and your apartment whatever in
the city itself. Okay, but the refuge, if you're, if you happen
to be taking a little walk outside the city, the area immediately
in the environs, the תחום tchum is still a refuge, you just
have to וישב, v'yashav, your dwelling has to be in the city.
כאן לקלוט כאן לדור. Kan liklot kan ladur. לדור, Ladur, the גמרא
Gemara says that you have to live in the city, תא שמע
דאין עושים שדה מגרש ולא מגרש שדה. ta shma d'ein osim sadeh
migrash v'lo migrash sadeh. A general הלכה halakha about the ערי הלויים
arei ha-Leviyim is that the תורה Torah says that the area outside
is a thousand אמה amah for, as I said, for, for like,
greenery, a thousand אמה amah for field, and that you're not allowed
to switch their designation. You can't make the field space a greenery
space, the greenery space a field space, ולא שדה מגרש ולא מגרש
שדה, v'lo sadeh migrash v'lo migrash sadeh, ולא מגרש עיר ולא עיר
מגרש, v'lo migrash ir v'lo ir migrash, and you can't make, you
can't turn the town part into a, like, suburban greenery and you
can't turn the greenery part, you can't start building there. So there's
a general הלכה halakha that you're not allowed to build, forget עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, because of the ערי הלויים, arei ha-Leviyim, you're not
allowed to build in the תחום tchum outside. So of course the
guy isn't allowed, able to live in the תחום tchum outside, you're
not allowed to build there. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב
ששת לא נצרכה אלא למחילות. Amar Rav Sheshet lo nitzercha ela l'mechilot.
Who says that living there requires building something? Maybe he could live
underground, in a cave. Okay, maybe he could be homeless and just,
you know, sleep there with a little tent. Okay, so there's a
separate הלכה, halakha, yes, in terms of the architecture or the structure,
you're not allowed to build, that's a הלכה halakha in the ערי
הלויים. arei ha-Leviyim. In terms of him, he's also not allowed to
live outside the city, he has to live in the city, but
the area around certainly serves as sanctuary. Yes, Mike.
So I'm just trying to understand something,
because reading the פסוקים, psukim, you could have taken it to mean
that the reason why this guy has to stay in the עיר
מקלט ir miklat is just for his own protection. Yes, not that
he has to stay there on like,
a—I understand, so the fact that there's a גמר דין gmar din
that puts him in the עיר מקלט ir miklat is showing that
actually that's not that, we're, the more we can make this part
of a בית דין Beis Din process and not like a Wild
West type of a thing, the more we're doing it. So his
going to the עיר מקלט ir miklat is part of the דין
din that's passed on him, there is a גמר דין, gmar din,
he has a מצוה mitzvah and a חיוב chiyuv to stay there.
So then he takes an איסור issur every time he goes out,
he's like violated some
עשה asei presumably, yes.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, now, יצא רוצח
חוץ לתחום, yatza rotzeach chutz la-tchum, now we get to the real.
really interesting question. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says that there's
a מצוה—bye Mitzvah Michael. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says it's
a מצוה Mitzvah for the גואל הדם Goel HaDam to kill him
and a רשות reshus for any person, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says no, it's only a רשות reshus for the גואל הדם Goel
HaDam and any other person, and here's the debate how to read
it, but our גירסא girsa is for any other person it would
be considered an act of murder. Others say for any other person
it wouldn't be an act of murder to kill him but would
not be—he doesn't have license to do it, but he wouldn't be
held liable. But anyway, our version is that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says, yeah basically, our version is that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
no, for any normal person it's an act of murder and even
for the גואל הדם Goel HaDam it's only a רשות. reshus. So
I think we can all more identify with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
meaning maybe partly we would like to say even for the גואל
הדם Goel HaDam it's not a רשות, reshus, but that's a פסוק,
pasuk, okay, that says the גואל הדם Goel HaDam is not held
liable, okay, and we would there, you know, and maybe that's again
the part that the תורה Torah is trying to reverse the reality
of vigilante justice, but you know it has to at least allow
it to some degree, like you can't totally make societal changes overnight,
and certainly if you have this הלכה halacha of the גואל הדם
Goel HaDam being—having רשות reshus to kill him, at least it'll keep
the guy in the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, okay, but רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili who says it's a מצוה Mitzvah of the
גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, like that seems—obviously seems much harder, you know,
I think for most of us to understand. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
ורצח גואל הדם את הרוצח. V'ratzach Goel HaDam es ha-rotzeiach. This—and you
know and it's basically the תורה Torah says, you know, if the
guy goes out of the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat and the גואל
הדם Goel HaDam kills the רוצח, rotzeiach, he is not held liable.
All right, that's the פסוק: pasuk: אין לו דמים. ein lo damim.
Okay, so מצוה? Mitzvah? So the רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili
would say ורצח, v'ratzach, he shall kill, it's a
מצוה. mitzvah. מצוה ביד גואל הדם. Mitzvah b'yad Goel HaDam. אין גואל
הדם—reshus—if Ein Goel HaDam there's no גואל הדם Goel HaDam to do
it, then רשות ביד כל אדם, reshus b'yad kol adam, everybody else
has permission to do it. דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי, Divrei Rabbi Yose
HaGlili, that's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says. רבי עקיבא
אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: No, רשות ביד גואל הדם, reshus b'yad Goel
HaDam, the גואל הדם Goel HaDam is permission, וכל אדם חייבין עליו,
v'chol adam chayavin alav, and every—and anybody else would be actually would
be an act of murder, at least that's our גירסא girsa of
the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי הגלילי? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yose
HaGlili? What's the reason of רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabbi Yose HaGlili? מי
כתיב אם רצח? Mi ksiv im ratzach? It could have said if
the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kills the רוצח rotzeiach he's not held
liable. It doesn't say that. It says ורצח גואל הדם את הרוצח,
v'ratzach Goel HaDam es ha-rotzeiach, which he's reading meaning should kill the
רוצח, rotzeiach, okay? ורבי עקיבא? V'Rabbi Akiva? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would
say, wait, מי כתיב ירצח? mi ksiv yirtzach? But it doesn't say
should kill. It's this verb, so they're both saying there's an ambiguity
of the verb. It's not explicit saying if it happens and it's
not explicit saying it should happen. It's saying: and the גואל הדם
Goel HaDam kills the רוצח. rotzeiach. Okay, so are you saying should
or are you saying if? So אמר מר זוטרא בר טוביה אמר
רב: Amar Mar Zutra bar Tuvia amar Rav: רוצח שיצא חוץ לתחום
ומצאו גואל הדם והרגו נהרג עליו. Rotzeiach sheyatza chutz lat-tchum u-metza'o Goel
HaDam v'harago neherag alav.
So now you get actually an opinion of an אמורא Amora
that rejects the two opinions of the תנאים Tannaim and says I
think the thing that for most of us we would more identify
with, which is: no, I'm sorry, even the גואל הדם Goel HaDam
is not able to kill the guy and if the גואל הדם
Goel HaDam kills the guy, it would be considered an act of
murder. So, but what do you mean? It's like an explicit פסוק.
pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says if the guy is out of the
city and the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kills him, אין לו דמים.
ein lo damim. So what—how do you—what do you do with the
פסוק? pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says, so before it asks about
the פסוק, pasuk, it says how do you disagree with the תנאים?
Tannaim? כמאן? K'man? Who is this going like? לא כרבי יוסי הגלילי
ולא כרבי עקיבא, Lo k'Rabbi Yose HaGlili v'lo k'Rabbi Akiva, not like
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili or רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. הוא
דאמר כי האי תנא, Hu d'amar ki hai tanna, he says like
the following תנא: Tanna: דתניא, d'tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא: Braisa:
רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: עד עמדו לפני העדה למשפט. ad
omdo lifnei ha-eidah l'mishpat. The פסוק pasuk says ולא ימות הרוצח עד
עמדו לפני העדה למשפט, v'lo yamut ha-rotzeiach ad omdo lifnei ha-eidah l'mishpat,
he shall not be killed until he stands for justice. Now that's
in the beginning of the discussion. It says somebody kills somebody, you
have to bring him to a court. You don't go ahead and
kill him because of the גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, you have to
bring him to a court and you have to see if he's
guilty or not. And then it goes on and says and if
he's guilty, you put him to death, and and if he's שוגג,
shogeg, then he goes to the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, meaning the
basic structure of the פסוקים psukim is, right?
I mean I won't write too much, but it's basically like this:
someone kills, okay, so it says don't kill him, don't let the
or don't have the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kill him, don't גואל
הדם Goel HaDam kill him until he stands trial. Okay, this is
the—this is my English translation of the פסוקים, psukim, of my summary
of the פסוקים: psukim: until he stands trial. Okay, that's עד עמדו
לפני העדה. ad omdo lifnei ha-eidah. Now if he stands trial, so
if he's guilty, if guilty, then executed.
If שוגג, shogeg, then he goes to the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat.
Okay, and then at the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, it says don't
leave,
because if the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kills him—the גואל הדם Goel
HaDam kills—you know, then he's—then he's like whatever, then
he's פטור, pattur, the גואל הדם Goel HaDam is פטור. pattur. Okay,
that's—that's the structure, imagine. So what this תנא Tanna saying is, is
that he is taking עד עמדו לפני העדה למשפט, ad omdo lifnei
ha-eidah l'mishpat, don't let the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kill him until
he stands trial, and applies that idea down here and says don't
leave the ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. Because if you leave the ערי
מקלט, Arei Miklat, the גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, with the fact that
he kills you, he's פטור, patur, yes, but not when he kills
you with vigilante justice. If you left the ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat,
this is again making the court in control of the whole thing.
By your leaving of the ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, you have passed
the death sentence on yourself. Okay, but what we're going to do
is, we will let the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kill this person,
but not on his own. עד עמדו לפני העדה למשפט. Ad amdo
lifnei ha'edah lamishpat. Okay, we're going to now hold a judgment case
about this person, find him guilty for having left the עיר מקלט,
Ir Miklat, and then let the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kill him.
Okay, so I don't know if that makes it better or worse.
Okay, you could say it makes it worse because now it's not
just, because if the guy leaves and the גואל הדם Goel HaDam
doesn't happen to find him and he sneaks and he gets back
in, no harm, no foul. This way, it maybe means what? Now
the court is going to go ahead and get evidence that the
guy left and slap him out? Like, it's not exactly clear. But
what it clearly is trying to do is have the court control
everything, completely remove the element of vigilante justice. Okay, so that's, so
let's take a look.
It says, does it mean the גואל הדם Goel HaDam has
to now bring him to the בית דין? Beit Din? Oh right,
so that could be, that's a nice way of reading it. That
only, that the גואל הדם Goel HaDam still needs to initiate, the
בית דין Beit Din isn't going to try to deal with it,
isn't going to try to get this guy killed. But if the
גואל הדם Goel HaDam says, I found you out of the city
and I'm going to bring you to בית דין Beit Din etc.,
maybe. So but the point is that yes, but he's not going
to be allowed to kill him by himself. He has to kill
him only under the auspices of the court. That's how we're reading
it. Okay. דתניא, De-tanya, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, עד עמדו
לפני העדה למשפט. Ad amdo lifnei ha'edah lamishpat. מה תלמוד לומר? Mah
talmud lomar?
Why is it saying that? לפי שנאמר, Lefi shene'emar, ורצח גואל הדם
את הרוצח. Ve-ratzach Goel HaDam et ha-rotzeach.
He'll kill him, that's what it says at the end, when he
steps out of the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. יכול
מיד? Yachol miyad? Maybe it means that he immediately has a right
to kill this guy who stepped out of the עיר מקלט. Ir
Miklat. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, עד עמדו לפני העדה למשפט. Ad amdo
lifnei ha'edah lamishpat.
No, he has to be brought to justice and, you know, I
like Gloria's suggestion, maybe by the גואל הדם Goel HaDam or whatever.
Anyway, the court has to authorize it. All right, but we can't
get rid of it completely. All right. Now, it says like this.
רבי יוסי ורבי עקיבא האי עד עמדו לפני העדה למשפט מאי דרשי
ביה? Rabbi Yossi ve-Rabbi Akiva hai ad amdo lifnei ha'edah lamishpat mai
darshi beih? What do they do with that פסוק? pasuk? You know,
that you need the guy to stand trial, which should be pretty
obvious. הוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, Hu miba'ei leih le-khidetanya, for the ברייתא
braita we talked about. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, מניין לסנהדרין
שראו אחד, minayin le-Sanhedrin sherau echad, so completely unrelated issue. Okay, I
mean because again, the top of the פסוקים pesukim here is talking
about מזיד, meizid, right? So here it's for the following הלכה. halacha.
מניין לסנהדרין שראו אחד שהרג
את הנפש שאין ממיתין אותו עד שיעמדו בבית דין אחר? Minayin le-Sanhedrin
sherau echad she-harag et ha-nefesh she-ein mamitin oto ad she-ya'amdu be-Beit Din
acher? A whole בית דין Beit Din saw a guy commit murder.
Maybe they should just, you know, sort of say, לא תהא שמיעה
גדולה מראיה, Lo tehei shemi'ah gedolah me-riyah, sit down and have trial
and find him guilty on the spot. No, that doesn't give the
guy a fair trial. So therefore, they have to, of these, this
בית דין Beit Din has to not serve as a בית דין
Beit Din and bring their testimony to another בית דין Beit Din
and have the other בית דין Beit Din פסקן pasken the guy.
How do you know you have to do that? תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, עד עמדו לפני העדה למשפט. Ad amdo lifnei ha'edah lamishpat. You
have to be able to stand trial in front of a בית
דין, Beit Din, you can't have the בית דין Beit Din immediately
just try you guilty and having seen it. Okay, עד שיעמוד בבית
דין אחר. Ad she-ya'amod be-Beit Din acher. Fine. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
אם יצא יצא הרוצח. Im yatzo yetzei ha-rotzeach. If the guy leaves
the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, then the גואל הדם Goel HaDam can
kill him. אין לי אלא במזיד. Ein li ela be-meizid. Now, I
only know if he left willingly, he is exposing himself to be
killed by the גואל הדם. Goel HaDam.
בשוגג מניין? Be-shogeg minayin? What happens if he accidentally stepped over the
boundary, right? He just got into a whole good conversation with his
friend and they were walking and talking and didn't realize that they
accidentally left the city bounds.
Or the גואל הדם Goel HaDam changed the boundary.
Oh yeah, whatever, right. So מניין? minayin? How do you know that
that also makes him, exposes him to the, to the גואל הדם?
Goel HaDam? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אם יצא יצא, Im yatzo yetzei,
מכל מקום, mi-kol makom, יצא יצא yatzo yetzei I think. So
the double language means however he finds himself out of the עיר
מקלט, Ir Miklat, he is liable. I mean, he can be, he
is vulnerable. והתניא? Ve-hatanya? But didn't we teach in a ברייתא, braita,
במזיד נהרג בשוגג גולה? Be-meizid neherag be-shogeg goleh? That if somebody steps
out of the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, if he did it willingly
he can be killed by the גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, if he
did it unwillingly he goes back into the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat.
By the way, notice the legal language here. It doesn't say במזיד
be-meizid the גואל הדם Goel HaDam can kill him. במזיד נהרג. Be-meizid
neherag. That sort of is evoking the idea that we saw before,
trying to turn this all into like, he's חייב מיתה chayav mitah
for leaving and then that, and therefore that, that sort of empowers
the גואל הדם Goel HaDam and maybe we even as a בית
דין Beit Din take over. Okay, but anyway, but it's only if
he willingly leaves the, the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. לא קשיא. Lo
kashya. That's not difficult. הא כמאן דאמר אמרינן דיברה תורה כלשון בני
אדם הא כמאן דאמר לא אמרינן דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. Ha
ke-man de-amar amrinan dibrah Torah ki-leshon benei adam ha ke-man de-amar lo
amrinan dibrah Torah ki-leshon benei adam. The question is, do you דורש
doresh יצא יצא, yatzo yetzei, the double language? If you say the
תורה Torah is just talking in the vernacular, so don't make a
big deal about the double language. So it's only if he leaves
willingly. If you say, if you say the double language means something,
then it's saying even if he leaves unwillingly or unwittingly. All right.
So, so that's the question of what if he leaves שוגג, shogeg,
is he exposed or not? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מסתברא, mistabra, it
makes sense, כמאן דאמר דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. ke-man de-amar dibrah
Torah ki-leshon benei adam. actually to read it the way this is
interesting how much do you go by hermeneutics and how much is
your interpretation of the פסוקים Psukim dictated by logic. So אביי Abaye
says he's not saying that general point that hermeneutically we should say
דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, dibra Torah kilshon b'nei adam, I think
most of the time we follow רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says
we don't say that and we דרשינן darshan extra words or extra
letters, but here he's saying that it makes sense to say to
read to not make a big deal of יצא יצא yatzo yetzei
and to say that even only if he leaves intentionally. But if
he leaves by accident he is not vulnerable to the גואל הדם.
goel hadam. Why does that make sense? שלא יהא סופו חמור מתחילתו.
shelo yehei sofo chamur mitchilato.
So his end judgment shouldn't be more weighty than his beginning. מה
תחילתו ma tchilato what happened when he actually killed the person? במזיד
נהרג b'meizid neherag if he killed somebody willingly he's put to death,
בשוגג גולה b'shogeg goleh if he killed somebody unwittingly he's exiled. So
אף סופו af sofo
even the end when he leaves the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, במזיד
נהרג b'meizid neherag it makes sense to say that he's only liable
for death in a willful act if he willingly leaves the עיר
מקלט. Ir Miklat. Right? I mean if he unwittingly killed somebody he
doesn't get killed so if he unwittingly leaves the עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat he shouldn't be killed. If he's going to be liable for
death which makes sense to limit it to a willful act, במזיד
נהרג בשוגג גולה. b'meizid neherag b'shogeg goleh. But by the way look
how we have turned this into a case of דין, din, right?
We've removed it from the vigilante justice. It's like the use of
the word שוגג, shogeg, מזיד, meizid, right? And it's like you know
and that so your judgment the judgment passed on this guy is
that he's deserving of death for having left the עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat but that's only if he does it במזיד. b'meizid. Anyway so
that changes the whole framing of what we're doing here. Yes.
And that's the difference between the תנאים Tannaim and the אמוראים. Amoraim.
The תנאים Tannaim
right I mean the תנאים Tannaim here are closer to the to
the Torah but even the תנאים Tannaim you had the בית דין
Beis Din controlling it sending the שני תלמידי חכמים. shnei talmidei chachamim.
I mean the Torah you had the בית דין Beis Din coming
and controlling of vigilante justice and you just have it being taken
even that process being taken even further here at the אמוראים Amora's
period. Okay. So now it says like this, תניא, tanya, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, תניא tanya we wrap it up,
תניא חדא tanya chada we taught in one ברייתא, Braita, אב שהרג
בנו נעשה לו גואל הדם. av sheharag bno na'aseh lo goel hadam.
A father God forbid accidentally killed his son, the other son the
guy's brother is now the גואל הדם goel hadam for his brother's
blood and can now kill his father. Okay man talk about Freud
would have such a field day.
Okay so one says yeah you're entitled to be a גואל הדם.
goel hadam. ותניא אידך v'tanya idach another ברייתא Braita says אין בנו
נעשה לו גואל הדם. ein bno na'aseh lo goel hadam. No a
son cannot be a גואל הדם goel hadam for his to avenge
his brother's blood against the father. לימא הא רבי יוסי הגלילי והא
רבי עקיבא. leima ha Rabbi Yossi HaGlili v'ha Rabbi Akiva.
So maybe this matches up. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili that
says it's a מצווה mitzvah so we want to maybe increase the
possibility of גואל הדם goel hadam and have it even a son
on a father. For רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva then obviously he has
misgivings about the whole thing and says a רשות reshut so he
would more sort of say no you know we're not going to
let son and father. So the גמרא Gemara says no, ותסברא בין
למאן דאמר מצווה בין למאן דאמר רשות מי שרי, v'tisbra bein l'man
d'amar mitzvah bein l'man d'amar reshut mi sharei, whether it's a מצווה
mitzvah or רשות reshut
why should it be allowed for a son against a father? והאמר
רבה בר רב הונא וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל לכל אין הבן
נעשה שליח לאביו להכותו ולקללו v'ha'amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna v'chen tana
d'vei Rabbi Yishmael l'chol ein haben na'aseh shaliach l'aviv lehakoto ulekallelo that
even though that a son cannot be a שליח בית דין shaliach
Beis Din to inflict the בית דין's Beis Din punishments on the
father. So if the person is the guy who gives מלקות malkut
for the בית דין Beis Din and the father is חייב מלקות
chayav malkut the son has to step down. Okay? Or somehow a
person deserves a קללה klalah to be put in חרם cherem and
this guy's normally the one who does it if it's his father
he has to step down. So if that's true everybody should say
the son can't be a גואל הדם. goel hadam. Notice by the
way subtly what we just did. We made the act of גואל
הדם goel hadam being a שליח בית דין. shaliach Beis Din. Right?
That's sort of what we've been doing all along right? How do
we know the son can't be a גואל הדם goel hadam against
the father? Because a son can't be a שליח בית דין shaliach
Beis Din to impose court punishments against the father. Right? So clearly
we're seeing the act of גואל הדם goel hadam as a type
of a שליח בית דין. shaliach Beis Din. חוץ ממסית. chutz mimesit.
The one exception is if the father is a seducer to idolatry.
שהרי אמרה תורה לא תחמול עליו ולא תכסה עליו sheharei amra Torah
lo tachmol alav v'lo techaseh alav have no compassion. So anyway everybody
should agree the son can't be a גואל הדם. goel hadam. אלא
לא קשיא הא בנו והא בן בנו. ela lo kashya ha bno
v'ha ben bno. The son can't be a גואל הדם. goel hadam.
The position that said a son can be a גואל הדם goel
hadam is if it is the grandson. A father killed the son
and the son's son is his father's גואל הדם goel hadam against
his grandfather. People get that? Okay so that's when it's allowed. Fine.
As I said Freud would have a field day. Moving on. אילן
שהוא עומד ilan shehu omed okay let's get this done.
אילן שהוא עומד בתוך התחום ונופו נוטה חוץ לתחום או מחוץ לתחום
ונופו נוטה בתוך התחום הכל הולך אחר הנוף. ilan shehu omed betoch
hatchum v'nofo noteh chutz latchum o michutz latchum v'nofo noteh betoch hatchum
hakol holech achar hanof. We can do this in eight minutes. So
here is a classic discussion in the גמרא Gemara of שדינן נופו
בתר עיקרו. shadina nofo basar ikar. or עיקרו בתר נופו, ikaro batar
nofo, usually it's the first, which is if you have a tree
that the stump is in one place, not the stump, the what's
it called, the trunk is in one place, and the top of
it, what's the top called? Crown. The crown is in another place.
Okay, this is your line. This is the עיר מקלט, ir miklat,
or I guess the edge of the תחום techum of the עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, and this is outside. Okay?
So if somebody is here, or somebody is in the tree or
out here under the tree or whatever, let's say he's in the
tree. Okay?
So
is this person in the עיר מקלט ir miklat or outside the
עיר מקלט? ir miklat? Okay? And then what if it's the reverse?
Okay? So the משנה Mishnah says, הכל הולך
אחר הנוף. hakol holech achar hanof. Okay?
It all goes by the נוף, nof, which sounds like even if
you're standing here, because the נוף nof is up here, in my
example part of the נוף nof is
it's a little confusing, and I don't know exactly what you would
do in that case. Okay, but if it's like this, right? None
of the נוף nof is like that. So even if you're standing
here, you're defined as being outside. Okay? So wherever you are in
the tree, if you're, you know, and what does that mean? Next
to the tree? If I'm on the tree?
Like do I have to actually be climbing the tree? Right? So
presumably, I'd like to limit this and assume it means that here
you are, you're actually somehow climbing the tree, or you're in it
to some degree. So anyway, your position is defined by where the
נוף nof is. That's what the משנה Mishnah says. Now, okay, normally
the normal approach, which רש"י Rashi points out, is the opposite: שדינן
נופו בתר עיקרו. shadinan nofo batar ikaro. Right? That you like
you say no matter where you are up here in the air,
we look at you where the thing is planted. But here it
says the opposite. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. רמינהי,
Remini, I'll ask you on this: אילן שהוא עומד בפנים ונוטה לחוץ.
Ilan shehu omeid bifnim venoteh lachutz.
So this is a question about eating מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay? And let's say you have your מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, you have to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and you're in
the tree. And this is like exactly this scenario, okay? The trunk
is in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the top is outside, or vice versa. או
עומד בחוץ ונוטה לפנים. O omeid bachutz venoteh lifnim. מכנגד החומה ולפנים
כלפנים מכנגד החומה ולחוץ כלחוץ.
Mikineged hachomah velifnim kelifnim mikineged hachomah
velachutz kelachutz.
This says the easiest thing: you are where you are. You imagine
the wall going straight up, right? And if you're here, you're here;
if you're there, you're there. We don't, you know, it doesn't matter
that you're in a tree. Wherever you are, you are. No questions
right now.
Okay. מעשר אעיר מקלט רמית? Maaser a-ir miklat ramit? You're trying to
make a contradiction between מעשר Maaser and עיר מקלט? ir miklat? מעשר
בחומה תלה רחמנא. Maaser bachomah talah rachmana.
מעשר, Maaser, the idea is that you have to be in the
walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay? As רש"י Rashi says, it says, so
רש"י Rashi quotes a פסוק: pasuk: לפני ה' אלהיך תאכלנו. lifnei Hashem
Elokecha tochelenu. I don't know how that emphasizes the חומה, chomah, but
somehow we understand that ירושלים Yerushalayim and its connection to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash or whatever, that is defined by being in the
walls. So we don't have this issue about where in the tree,
it's just a question: in the walls, in the airspace of the
walls, or not in the airspace of the walls. עיר מקלט בדירה
תלה רחמנא. Ir miklat bedirah talah rachmana.
But in עיר מקלט, ir miklat, it says: כי בעיר מקלטו ישב.
Ki be-ir miklato yeishev.
It's where you consider to be dwelling. Okay? בנופו מידייר בעיקרו לא
מידייר. Benofo midayer be-ikaro lo midayer.
People might be able to make a treehouse and dwell in the
crown, but nobody dwells in the trunk. So therefore, the question I
ask here is not where are you, but where are you dwelling?
And therefore, if you're in a tree and I said where right
now are you dwelling, I would say, well, you're dwelling in the
crown, even though you're not in the crown, but that is the
place where it's fit to be dwelling. That's what the גמרא Gemara
says. Now we're not going to stick with this answer. Okay? ורמי
מעשר אמעשר. Verami Maaser a-Maaser. But there's a contradiction even when it
comes to מעשר. Maaser. דתניא: Detanya: בירושלים הלך אחר הנוף. BiYerushalayim halach
achar hanof. When it comes to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, or תנן, tenan, this
is a משנה Mishnah in מעשרות, Maasrot, which means when it comes
to eating מעשר, Maaser, are you in ירושלים Yerushalayim or not? It
says go by where the נוף nof is. ובעיר מקלט הלך אחר
הנוף. Uve-ir miklat halach achar hanof. And by עיר מקלט ir miklat
go after the נוף. nof. So that says מעשר Maaser and עיר
מקלט ir miklat are the same. But here's a משנה. Mishnah. So
now we have a contradiction: a משנה Mishnah says you go by
the נוף, nof, by the crown, but the ברייתא Braita says by
מעשר Maaser you go by where you are. So how do you
reconcile it? אמר רב כהנא לא קשיא. Amar Rav Kahana lo kashya.
It's not difficult. הא רבי יהודה והא רבנן. Ha Rabi Yehuda ve-ha
Rabbanan. It's a debate. דתניא, Detanya, that's the most obvious thing to
say, one says one, one says the other, it's a debate. רבי
יהודה אומר: Rabi Yehuda omeir: במערה הלך אחר פתחה. Bimearah holech achar
pitchah.
Let's say you have a case like this, and you're in a
cave. Okay? And here you are in the cave. Here's the line,
like dividing in ירושלים Yerushalayim and out, and you're here. Okay? So
he says you go where the opening is. If the opening is
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, then you're in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. If the opening is
out, you're out. Which makes a lot of sense since that's the
only sort of, you know, that's the access point. Okay? במערה הלך
אחר פתחה, Bimearah holech achar pitchah, you go by the opening. That
defines where you are even if you're deep inside the cave, you're
considered in ירושלים Yerushalayim if the opening is in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay,
באילן הולך אחר נופו, be-ilan holech achar nofo,
and by the tree you go by the the crown, which is
a little funny because you might think that the parallel to the
opening is the trunk. The trunk is the access point. Okay, but
for whatever reason he says that the crown determines where you are
and that is and that's the position that says both for ירושלים
Yerushalayim and for מעשר, Maaser, both for מעשר Maaser and for עיר
מקלט Ir Miklat you go by the crown. That's a רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda position. So
and the other position we haven't said explicitly, but the other position
would say at least for מעשר, Maaser, and maybe also for עיר
מקלט, Ir Miklat, maybe it's all the same. We're dropping that distinction.
You go where you are. So now we're saying the רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda position is you go by the crown, and there's an
opposing position that says you go by wherever you happen to be,
whichever airspace you're in. End of discussion. Now the גמרא Gemara has
a question. אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי יהודה גבי מעשר לחומרא. eima d'shamat
lei l'Rabbi Yehuda gabei Maaser l'chumra.
One minute. And now the funny thing is there's nothing forcing the
גמרא Gemara to say this, but the גמרא Gemara just is assumes
you can't really go by the crown בין לחומרא בין לקולא. bein
l'chumra bein l'kula. רש״י Rashi says the reason is because elsewhere we
have a general principle of שדינן נופו בתר עיקרו. shadinan nofo batar
ikaro. The general principle is the crown follows the trunk. So even
when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you go by the crown, the
גמרא's Gemara going to say you can't mean that even לקולא. l'kula.
You have to mean that we're מחמיר machmir that way but not
that we would say it fully. What does it mean to be
מחמיר? machmir? Well by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni there are there are
חומרות chumros and קולות kulos being in ירושלים Yerushalayim and out. If
this is ירושלים Yerushalayim and this is out, so in ירושלים Yerushalayim
you eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheni but you can't be פודה. podeh.
And out, you don't eat
and you can be פודה. podeh. So to be מחמיר machmir means
if you're here, we'll consider you out of ירושלים Yerushalayim לחומרא l'chumra
to say don't eat, but we won't let you be פודה podeh
because the trunk is here, so we're going to say also don't
be פודה. podeh. All right, which basically means if you think about
it, you know what that means? It means that we'd that
wherever you are like if you're in the נופו nofo of a
tree, if you're here you're fully in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But if you're
the נופו nofo of a tree, you're basically we just put both
חומרות chumros on top of you. All right, so that's how the
גמרא Gemara is choosing to read רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. It's not
possible to say that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really means you fully
go by the נוף nof the way רש״י Rashi says it is
cause we always go by the trunk. So therefore if he says
it, it means they're just going to be strict and say we're
going to be strict both ways. Let's read that. אימא דשמעת ליה
לרבי יהודה גבי מעשר לחומרא. eima d'shamat lei l'Rabbi Yehuda gabei Maaser
l'chumra. עיקרו בחוץ ונופו בפנים ikaro bachutz v'nofo bifnim if the trunk
is outside and the foliage is inside, כי היכי דבנופו לא מצי
פריק ליה ki heichi d'benofo lo matzi parik lei the same way
where the trunk is in ירושלים Yerushalayim you can't redeem, excuse me,
the נוף, nof, the foliage is inside, you can't redeem. בעיקרו נמי
לא מצי פריק ליה, be-ikaro nami lo matzi parik lei, so also
at the trunk you're not going to be able to redeem.
עיקרו מבפנים ונופו מבחוץ ikaro mibifnim v'nofo mibachutz if the trunk is
inside and the נוף nof is outside. כי היכי דנופו לא מצי
אכיל ki heichi d'nofo lo matzi achil the same way you can't
eat with the נוף nof because that's outside בלא פדייה, belo pidyah,
בעיקרו נמי לא מצי אכיל בלא פדייה be-ikaro nami lo matzi achil
belo pidyah also by the trunk. So actually it says you go
מחמיר machmir both ways in both of these. Okay, that this guy
follows out. Yeah, I think did I say it wrong? I think
I was saying it wrong because he says you follow the נוף,
nof, meaning he's talking about this guy, sorry I thought I was
talking about this guy. Okay, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you
follow the נוף. nof. So if a guy is in the tree
is in the trunk, he follows the נוף, nof, but he follows
it לחומרא. l'chumra. Meaning so if he's here in ירושלים Yerushalayim and
the נוף nof is out, he has to be מחמיר machmir and
he basically can't eat. Okay, but he's not able to be פודה,
podeh, he also has to be מחמיר machmir and say don't be
פודה. podeh. All right, basically we're מחמיר machmir always, even though he
says you go by the נוף. nof.
According to the גמרא Gemara
is choosing to read רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says you only
go by the נוף nof to be strict. All right, I'm sorry
if I think I confused people a little bit, but I think
you get the idea. Okay, he's not saying you fully go by
the נוף, nof, he's saying you only go by the נוף nof
to be strict. So even though we take the guy at the
tree and imagine him in the נוף, nof, it's only to be
strict that way. We're not going to really fully be לקולא l'kula
that way. The guy's at the trunk, the trunk as רש״י Rashi
says is the more important thing. So if the guy's at the
trunk we're not going to be lenient and consider him in the
נוף, nof, we're going to be strict and consider him in the
נוף. nof. Okay, that's the key point.
So now the גמרא Gemara says אבל גבי עיר מקלט, aval gabei
Ir Miklat, but by an עיר מקלט Ir Miklat it seems you
know it would also be a קולא. kula. How would it be
a קולא? kula? בשלמא עיקרו בחוץ ונופו בפנים bishlama ikaro bachutz v'nofo
bifnim if the trunk is on the outside and the crown is
on the inside... inside and the on the outside and the נוף
*nof* is on the inside and he's on the trunk, כי היכי
דבנופו לא מצי קטיל ליה בעיקרו נמי לא מצי קטיל ליה *ki
heichi debenofo lo matzi katlei be'ikara nami lo matzi katlei*. So to
be מחמיר *machmir* means to say the גואל הדם *goel hadam* isn't
allowed to kill. Okay, so if this is the case
here, okay, if this is the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*
and this is outside, okay, so we can understand an approach, we
would always be strict to assume him in the נוף *nof*, means
in this case he's out of the עיר מקלט *ir miklat* but
we're going to be strict and assume that it's like he's in
the נוף *nof*, okay, and we're going to say that basically he
can, what do you call it, that he's protected, okay, that's being
strict. Are people with me here? Yeah, okay, that's being strict.
Okay, strict means assume he's in.
Assume he's in the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*. Okay, that we get,
says the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, אלא עיקרו בפנים ונופו בחוץ *ella ikaro
bifnim venofo bachutz*, but if it's the opposite, okay, if this is
the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*
and this is outside,
how can we go ahead and say that we're going to consider
him to be go by the נוף *nof* that's only being לקולא
*lekula*? It's exposing him to be killed. All right, so in that
case, אלא *ella*,
where were we? עיקרו בפנים ונופו בחוץ כי היכי דבנופו מצי קטיל
ליה בעיקרו נמי מצי קטיל ליה *ikaro bifnim venofo bachutz ki heichi
debenofo matzi katlei be'ikara nami matzi katlei*, would you say the same
way a guy up here could be killed, down here he could
be killed? Really, in the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*, at the trunk
of the tree, we're going to let him be killed? That's following
the נוף לקולא *nof lekula*, that's being a little, that's going, getting
a little, that's crazy, says the גמרא *Gemara*, that we should say
that. הא גברא קאי *ha gavra kai*,
he's inside the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*. We should pretend he's up
in the top of the foliage of the tree to let him
get killed? Okay. So אמר רבא *amar Rava*, says רבא *Rava*, בעיקרו
דכולי עלמא לא פליגי *be'ikaro dechulei alma lo peligi*. Fine, you're right.
We're only talking לחומרא *lechumra*. In this case where the guy is
down here, everybody would agree that he's protected even if the נוף
*nof* is up there. בעיקרו דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא מצי קטיל
*be'ikaro dechulei alma lo peligi delo matzi katil* that you can't kill
him. קאי בנופו ויכול להורגו בחיצין ובצרורות דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דמצי
קטיל ליה *kai benofo veyachol lehorgo bechitzin ubitzroros dechulei
alma lo peligi dematzi katil leih*. If the guy however is up
here, okay, and people can throw things at him and kill him
like the גואל הדם *goel hadam*, you can kill him. Up here
you're out of the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*, down here in the
עיר מקלט *ir miklat* and we're not going to imagine from here,
we're not going to go by the נוף *nof* in order to
allow you to be exposed. So what's the debate? So כי פליגי
*ki peligi*, what's the debate? דמהוי עיקרו דרגא לנוף *demahavei ikaro darga
lenof*. Can the guy, now this is not at all what it
sounds like in the משנה *Mishnah*, this is a complete reread, can
the גואל הדם *goel hadam* come in into the עיר מקלט *ir
miklat* and use the trunk to climb up to him and get
to him? Okay, I'm going to kill him out of the עיר
מקלט *ir miklat* because I'm going to kill him up in the
tree, but I'm going to go into the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*
to get access to him in order to climb up the tree
to get to him. It's a completely different discussion. דרגא לנופו *darga
lenofo*. מר סבר הוי עיקרו דרגא לנופו ומר סבר לא הוי עיקרו
דרגא לנופו *mar savar havei ikaro darga lenofo umar savar lo havei
ikaro darga lenofo*. Fine, that's not פשט *pshat* at all but whatever.
רב אשי אמר *Rav Ashi amar*, מאי אחרי נוף אף אחרי נוף
*mai acharei nof af acharei nof*. And רב אשי *Rav Ashi* says
no, when the משנה *Mishnah* says you go by the נוף *nof*,
it means you're מקיל *meikil* by the נוף *nof*. Okay, if the
guy is here and the נוף *nof* is outside, of course you're
going to go with where he is. You're going to have the
most expansive read to protect him is the point. So if he's
in, if he's inside and the נוף *nof* is outside, he's inside.
But if he's outside and the נוף *nof* is inside, we'll go
by the נוף *nof* in order to imagine him inside and in
order to protect him. So it's similar to what the גמרא *Gemara*
says before. We will go, if the guy is at the trunk
and the נוף *nof* is somewhere else, so when רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says you go by the נוף *nof*, again the way רש"י
*Rashi* explains it is nobody is going to say that if you're
at the trunk you're more in the top of the tree than
you're at the bottom. So when רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says you
go by the top if you're at the trunk, it means we're
going to be מחמיר *machmir* that way. All right, so by מעשר
שני *Maaser Sheni* being מחמיר *machmir* that way has its implications about,
but by עיר מקלט *ir miklat* what it means is if you're
at the trunk and you're in the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*, you're
in the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*. Of course, the most obvious thing
is you are where you are at the trunk. But if you're
at the trunk and you're outside and the foliage is inside, then
we're going to protect you, which is called being מחמיר *machmir*, and
imagine it as if you're inside and say you're also protected while
you're at the trunk. All right, I hope that was pretty clear,
a little complicated,
but I hope you got the basic and we will pick up
here tomorrow.